<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Automachia, or the self-conflict of a Christian</title>
            <author>Goodwin, George, fl. 1607-1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112828</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848071</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848071</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13146</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13146)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 714:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Automachia, or the self-conflict of a Christian</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, George, fl. 1607-1620.</author>
                  <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melch. Bradwood for Edward Blovnt,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By George Goodwin. Translator's preface signed I[oshua]. S[ylvester].</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Goodwin's Latin original is unknown--DNB.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁶ B-C D⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:1"/>
            <p>AVTOMACHIA,
OR
<hi>The</hi> SELF-CONFLICT <hi>of a</hi>
Chriſtian.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST NOBLE,
vertuous, and learned Lady, the
<hi>Lady</hi> MARY NEVIL,
One of the Daughters of the right Honourable
<hi>the Earle of</hi> DORCET, <hi>Lord</hi>
High. Treaſurer of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:3"/>
               <l>Adde but an A, to Romanize your Name,</l>
               <l>ANOTHER PALLAS is your <hi>Anagram:</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>(videlicet)</p>
            <lg>
               <l>MARIA NEVILA.</l>
               <l>ALIA MINERVA.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13146:3"/>
               <l>MAdame, your loue to <hi>learning</hi> and the <hi>learned,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(In ſuch an Age, ſo full of <hi>Art's</hi> neglect)</l>
               <l>Right worthily to your rare Selfe hath earned</l>
               <l>The loue of <hi>learning</hi> and the <hi>learned</hi> ſect;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:4"/>
               <l>Whereby, your <hi>Name</hi> already is eterned</l>
               <l>In <hi>MEMORIE</hi>'s faire <hi>TEMPLE</hi> hie erect:</l>
               <l>And there, deuoutly at your <hi>VERTV</hi>'s Shrine,</l>
               <l>J humbly <hi>Offer</hi> this poore <hi>MITE</hi> of mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13146:4"/>
               <l>Too ſmall a <hi>Preſent</hi> to ſo great a <hi>GRACE,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And too vnworthy of your <hi>Worthineſſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saue that the <hi>Matter</hi> ſo exceeds the <hi>Maſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That oft (perhaps) a <hi>Greater</hi> may be <hi>leſſe:</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:5"/>
               <l>For, you may ſee, within this little <hi>Glaſſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>LITTLE-WORLD</hi>'s Great-Little-Minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Man's</hi> ſtrife with <hi>Man:</hi> our <hi>Fleſh</hi> &amp; <hi>Spirit</hi> in Duel:</l>
               <l>Couragious-Cowards, too <hi>Self</hi>-kindely-cruel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13146:5"/>
               <l>Vouchſafe t' accept then this <hi>ſmall New-yeres-Gift,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With th' humble <hi>Vowes</hi> of a diſ-Aſtred <hi>Muſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That lauiſhly hath ſow'n her ſeeds of Thrift</l>
               <l>So high and drie that yet no <hi>Fruit</hi> enſues;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:6"/>
               <l>Els need ſhe not haue made ſo hard a Shift,</l>
               <l>Nor this <hi>Small Gift</hi> ſo greatly to excuſe:</l>
               <l>But, ſith (as yet) ſhe cannot what ſhe would,</l>
               <l>Madame, accept her <hi>Zeale,</hi> and what ſhe could.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:6"/>
            <closer>
               <signed>Moſt deuoted<lb/>
to your Honorable Vertues,<lb/>
                  <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:7"/>
            <p>AVTOMACHIA,
OR
<hi>The</hi> SELF-CONFLICT <hi>of a
Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>VErtue I loue, I leane to Vice: I blame</l>
               <l>This wicked World, yet I embrace the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:8"/>
               <l>I clime to Heauen, I cleaue to Earth: I both</l>
               <l>Too-loue my Selfe, and yet my Selfe I loath:</l>
               <l>Peaceleſſe, I Peace purſue: In Ciuill Warre,</l>
               <l>With, and againſt my Selfe, I ioine, I iarre:</l>
               <l>I burne, I freeze: I fall downe, I ſtand faſt:</l>
               <l>Well-ill I fare: I glory, though diſgrac't:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:8"/>
               <l>I die a-liue: I triumph put to flight:</l>
               <l>I feed on Cares: In Teares I take delight:</l>
               <l>My ſiaue (baſe-braue) I ſerue: I roame at large</l>
               <l>In Libertie, yet lie in Gaolers charge:</l>
               <l>I ſtrike, and ſtroake my ſelfe: I kyndly keen</l>
               <l>Work mine own woe, rub my gal, rouz my ſpleen:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:9"/>
               <l>Oft in my ſleepe, to ſee rare dreames, I dreame;</l>
               <l>Waking, mine eye doth ſcarſe diſcern a beame:</l>
               <l>My minde's ſtrange <hi>Megrim</hi> whirling to and fro,</l>
               <l>Now thruſts me hither, thither then doth throw:</l>
               <l>In diuers Factions I my Selfe diuide;</l>
               <l>And all I trie, and flie to euery ſide:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:9"/>
               <l>What I but now deſir'd, I now diſdaine:</l>
               <l>What late I weigh'd not, now I wiſh againe:</l>
               <l>To-day, to-morrow; This, that; Now, anon:</l>
               <l>All, nothing craue I (euer neuer-one).</l>
               <l>Dull Combatant, vnready for the field,</l>
               <l>Too-tardie take I after wounds my ſhield:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:10"/>
               <l>Still hurri'd head-long to vnlawfull things,</l>
               <l>Down-dragging Vice me downward eaſly dings:</l>
               <l>But ſacred Vertue climes ſo hard and hie,</l>
               <l>That hardly can I her ſteepe ſteps deſcrie.</l>
               <l>Both Right and Wrong with me indifferent are:</l>
               <l>My Luſt is Law: what I deſire, I dare:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:10"/>
               <l>(Is there ſo foule a Fault, ſo fond a Fact,</l>
               <l>Which Follie aſking, Furie dares not act?).</l>
               <l>But Art-leſſe-hart-leſſe in Religion's cauſe</l>
               <l>(To doo her Leſſons, and defend her Lawes)</l>
               <l>The all-proofe armor of my GOD I loſe,</l>
               <l>Flie from my Charge, and yeeld it to his foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:11"/>
               <l>Guiltie of ſinne, ſinn's puniſhment I ſhunne,</l>
               <l>But not the guilt, before th' offence be done:</l>
               <l>For, how could ſhunning of a ſinne, enſew</l>
               <l>To be occaſion of another new?</l>
               <l>Oft and againe at the ſame ſtone I trip</l>
               <l>(As if I learn'd by falling, not to ſlip).</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:11"/>
               <l>Aliue I periſh and my Selfe vndoo,</l>
               <l>Mine eyes (ſelf-wiſe) witting and willing too.</l>
               <l>Sicke, to my Selfe I run for my reliefe,</l>
               <l>So, ſicker of my Phyſicke than my griefe:</l>
               <l>For, while I ſeeke my ſwelting Thirſt to ſwage,</l>
               <l>Another Thirſt more ragingly doth rage:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:12"/>
               <l>While, burnt to death, to coole me I deſire,</l>
               <l>With flames my flames, with ſulphur que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch I fire:</l>
               <l>While that I ſtriue my wauing Waues to ſtop,</l>
               <l>More wauingly, they waue aboue my top:</l>
               <l>Thus am I cur'd, this is my common eaſe,</l>
               <l>My medcine ſtill worſe than my worſt diſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:12"/>
               <l>My ſores with ſores, my wounds w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wounds I heale,</l>
               <l>While, to my Selfe my Selfe I ſtill conceale.</l>
               <l>O what leud Leagues! what Truces make I ſtill</l>
               <l>With Sin, and Sathan, and my wanton Will!</l>
               <l>What ſlight Occaſions do I take to ſin!</l>
               <l>What ſillic Traines am I entrapped in!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:13"/>
               <l>What idle cloaks for'crimes! What nets to hide</l>
               <l>Notorious ſinnes, already long deſcri'd!</l>
               <l>I write in Ice, Windes witnes, ſign'd with Showrs,</l>
               <l>I will redeeme my foule Life's former howrs,</l>
               <l>And ſoon the ſwindge of Cuſtom (whirlwind like)</l>
               <l>Rapting my paſſion (euer Faſhion ſicke)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:13"/>
               <l>Tranſports me to the contrary: alone,</l>
               <l>Faint Guard of Goodnes; Arm-les Champion.</l>
               <l>My morrall Taſte doth nothing ſweeter finde,</l>
               <l>Than what is bitter to th'immortall minde.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegypt</hi>'s fat Fleſh-pots I am longing-for,</l>
               <l>Th'eternall <hi>Manna</hi> I do euen abhor.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:14"/>
               <l>World's Monarch <hi>Mammon</hi> (Dropſie myſtical)</l>
               <l>Crown'd round-fac't Goddeſſe, coined <hi>Belial,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Midas</hi> Deſire, the Miſer's only Truſt,</l>
               <l>The ſacred hunger of <hi>Pactolian</hi> duſt,</l>
               <l>Gold, Gold bewitches me, &amp; frets accurſt</l>
               <l>My greedy throat with more than <hi>Dipſian</hi> Thirſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:14"/>
               <l>My minde's a Gulfe, whoſe gaping nought can ſtuffe:</l>
               <l>My hart a hell that neuer hath enough:</l>
               <l>The more I haue, I craue, and leſſe content:</l>
               <l>In ſtore moſt poore, in plentie indigent:</l>
               <l>For, of theſe Cates how much-ſoe'r I cramme,</l>
               <l>It doth not ſtop my mouth, but ſtretch the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:15"/>
               <l>Sweet Vſurie's inceſtuous Intereſt,</l>
               <l>For Dallers, dolours hoordeth in my cheſt:</l>
               <l>The World's-ſlaue Profit, &amp; the Minds-ſlut Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</l>
               <l>(Inſatiat both, both boundleſſe, both paſt meaſure,</l>
               <l>This, <hi>Cleopatra;</hi> That, <hi>Sardanapale</hi>)</l>
               <l>For huge Annoyes, bring Toyes but ſhort &amp; ſmall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:15"/>
               <l>O Miracle! begot by Heau'n of Earth</l>
               <l>(Of Minde diuine, of Body brute by birth)</l>
               <l>O what a Monſter am I to depaint!</l>
               <l>Half-friend, half-fiend; half-ſauage, half-a-ſaint.</l>
               <l>Higher than my Fier doth my groſſe Earth aſpire:</l>
               <l>My raging Fleſh my reſtleſſe Force doth tire:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:16"/>
               <l>And, drunk w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world's Muſt, &amp; deep ſunk in ſleep,</l>
               <l>My Spirit (the Spie that wary watch ſhould keep)</l>
               <l>Betraies alas (woe that I truſt it ſo)</l>
               <l>My Soule's deere kingdome to her deadly foe.</l>
               <l>Through Care's <hi>Charybdis,</hi> and rough Gulfs of Griefe,</l>
               <l>Star-lar-boord run I, ſailing all my life</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:16"/>
               <l>On merrie-ſorrie Seas: my Winde, my Will;</l>
               <l>My Ship, my Fleſh; my Senſe, my Pilot ſtill.</l>
               <l>As in a moſt ſeditious Common-Weale,</l>
               <l>Within my breſt I feele my beſt rebell:</l>
               <l>Againſt their Prince my furious People riſe:</l>
               <l>Their awleſſe Prince dares his owne Law deſpiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:17"/>
               <l>Mine <hi>Eue</hi>'s an Out-law, and my ſtruggling Twins</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> neuer can be friends;</l>
               <l>Such deadly feud, ſuch diſcord, ſuch deſpight</l>
               <l>(Euer betweene Brethren) ſuch continuall fight.</l>
               <l>What's done in me, another doth, not I;</l>
               <l>Yet, both (alas) my Gueſt and Enemie:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:17"/>
               <l>My minde vnkinde (ſuborned by my foe)</l>
               <l>Indeed, within me, but not with me tho;</l>
               <l>Neere, yet farre off: in fleſhly lees beſoil'd,</l>
               <l>And with the World's contagious filth defil'd.</l>
               <l>I am too narrow for mine owne Deſires:</l>
               <l>My Selfe denies me what my Selfe requires:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:18"/>
               <l>I feare and hope: careleſſe, in Cares I languiſh:</l>
               <l>Hungry, too full: dry-drinking, ſugred-anguiſh:</l>
               <l>Wearie of life, merrie in death: I ſucke</l>
               <l>Wine from the Pumice, Hony from the Rocke.</l>
               <l>On thornes my grapes: on garlik growes my roſe:</l>
               <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crums my ſums: fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flint my fountain flowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:18"/>
               <l>In ſhowrs of teares mine houres of fears I mourn,</l>
               <l>My looks to brooks, my beams to ſtreams I turn:</l>
               <l>Yet in this Torrent of my Torment riſe</l>
               <l>I ſink annoies, and drink the ioies of life.</l>
               <l>Dim Light, brim Night, Beames wauing cloudy-cleer:</l>
               <l>Vnſtable State, void Hope, vain Helpe, far-neer:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:19"/>
               <l>Falſe-true Perſuaſion, Lawleſſe Lawfulneſſe:</l>
               <l>Confuſed method; milde-wilde, Warlike Peace:</l>
               <l>Diſordered Order, Mournfull merriments:</l>
               <l>Dark-day, wrong-way; dull, double-diligence:</l>
               <l>Infamous Fame, know'n Error, ſkilleſſe Skill:</l>
               <l>Mad Minde, rude Reaſon, an vnwilling Will:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:19"/>
               <l>A healthy plague, a wealthy want, poore treaſure:</l>
               <l>A pleaſing Torment, a tormenting Pleaſure:</l>
               <l>An odious Loue, an ougly Beauty; baſe</l>
               <l>Reproachfull Honour, a diſgracefull Grace:</l>
               <l>A fruitleſſe Fruit, a drie diſ-flowred Flower:</l>
               <l>A feeble Force, a conquered Conquerour:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:20"/>
               <l>A ſickly Health, dead Life, and reſtleſſe Reſt:</l>
               <l>Theſe are the Comforts of my Soule diſtreſt.</l>
               <l>O how I like! diſlike! deſire! diſdaine!</l>
               <l>Repell! repeale! loath! and delight againe!</l>
               <l>O what! whom! whether! (neither fleſh nor fiſh)</l>
               <l>How weary of, the ſame againe I wiſh!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:20"/>
               <l>I will, I nill; I nill, I will: my Minde</l>
               <l>Perſuading This, my Luſt to That inclin'd:</l>
               <l>My looſe Affection (<hi>Proteus</hi>-like) appeeres</l>
               <l>In euery forme: at-once it frownes and fleeres,</l>
               <l>Mine ill-good Will is vaine and variable:</l>
               <l>My (<hi>Hydra</hi>) Fleſh buds Heads innumerable:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:21"/>
               <l>My Minde's a Maze, a Labyrinth my Reaſon:</l>
               <l>Mine Eye (falſe Spie) the doore to Fancie's trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</l>
               <l>My rebell Senſe (Self-ſoothing) ſtill affects</l>
               <l>What it ſhould flie; what it ſhould plie, neglects.</l>
               <l>My flitting Hope with Paſſion-ſtormes is toſt</l>
               <l>But now to Heau'n, anon to Hell almoſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:21"/>
               <l>Concording Diſcord kils me, and againe</l>
               <l>Diſcording Concord doth my life maintaine.</l>
               <l>My Selfe at-once I both diſpleaſe and pleaſe:</l>
               <l>Without my Selfe my Selfe I faine would ſeaſe:</l>
               <l>For, my too-much of Mee, mee much annoyes;</l>
               <l>And my Selfe's Plentie my poore Selfe deſtroyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:22"/>
               <l>Who ſeeks mee in Mee in mee ſhall not finde</l>
               <l>Mee as my Selfe: <hi>Hermaphrodite,</hi> in minde</l>
               <l>I am at-once Male, Female, Neuter: yet</l>
               <l>What e'r I am, I am not Mine (I weet):</l>
               <l>I am not with my Selfe (as I conceiue)</l>
               <l>Wretch that I am; my Selfe my Selfe deceiue:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:22"/>
               <l>Vnto my Selfe, my Selfe my Selfe betray:</l>
               <l>I from my Selfe baniſh my Selfe away:</l>
               <l>My Selfe agree not with my Selfe a iot:</l>
               <l>Know not my Selfe; I haue my Selfe forgot:</l>
               <l>Againſt my Selfe my Selfe moue iarres vniuſt:</l>
               <l>I truſt my Selfe, and I my Selfe diſtruſt:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:23"/>
               <l>My Selfe I follow, and my Selfe I flie:</l>
               <l>Beſides my Selfe, and in my Selfe am I:</l>
               <l>My Selfe am not my Selfe, another Same:</l>
               <l>Vnlike my Selfe, and like my Selfe I am:</l>
               <l>Selfe-fond, Selfe-furious: and thus, wayward Elfe,</l>
               <l>I can not liue with nor without my Selfe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:23"/>
            <head>A comfortable Exhortation to
the Chriſtian, in his
Self-Conflict.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHy, ſilly Man, ſicke of exceeding Griefe,</l>
               <l>What boots it thee, vncertaine of thy life,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:24"/>
               <l>Of thy Diſeaſe to make ſo much a-doo:</l>
               <l>Thou coward Souldier, and vntoward too?</l>
               <l>Away with Feare: and, Death of Death and Hell,</l>
               <l>Meet armes with armes, &amp; darts with darts repell:</l>
               <l>So the firſt Onſet in this doubtfull Fray,</l>
               <l>Shall towards Heau'n make thee an eaſie way:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:24"/>
               <l>And open wide thoſe Gates (ſo hardly wonne)</l>
               <l>Where ſnowie-winged Victorie doth wunne.</l>
               <l>Thou muſt be valiant, and with dauntleſſe breſt,</l>
               <l>Ruſh through the thickeſt, run vpon the beſt</l>
               <l>Of th'aduerſe Hoaſt; and on their flight &amp; foile,</l>
               <l>Build noble Tropheis of triumphant ſpoile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:25"/>
               <l>For, this world's Prince, dark Limbo's Potentate</l>
               <l>Driſts Earth's deſtruction; and with deadly hate</l>
               <l>(Still ſtrife-full) labours, and by all meanes ſeeks</l>
               <l>To trouble all, and Heauen with Hell to mix.</l>
               <l>Great War within there is, great War without,</l>
               <l>With Fleſh &amp; Blood, and with the World about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:25"/>
               <l>On this ſide, ſmiling <hi>Hope</hi> with ſmootheſt brow</l>
               <l>Falſe-promiſeth long Peace and Plentie too:</l>
               <l>On that ſide, ſallow <hi>Feare</hi> with fainting breath</l>
               <l>Checks thoſe proud thoughts, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> threats of war &amp; death;</l>
               <l>And, weary of it Selfe, it Selfe diſtruſts,</l>
               <l>It Selfe deſtroyes, and to Confuſion thruſts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:26"/>
               <l>And ignorant of it Selfe's good (till triall)</l>
               <l>In ielous rage it euen betraies the loyall.</l>
               <l>Heer cloud-brow'd <hi>Sorow,</hi> whirl-wind-like it hies,</l>
               <l>Th'amatted Minde to toſſe and tyrannize.</l>
               <l>There, dimpled <hi>Ioy</hi> nimbly enringeth round</l>
               <l>Her gaudie Troops that ſtand vpon no ground;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:26"/>
               <l>Whoſe brittle gloſſe and glory, laſts and ſhines,</l>
               <l>As ſtubble-fier, and duſt before the windes.</l>
               <l>What ſhould I ſpeake of all the ſnarefull Wiles,</l>
               <l>And cunning colours of myſterious Guiles,</l>
               <l>Wherwith death's Founder &amp; our life's drad Foe</l>
               <l>Improuident Man-kinde doth ouerthrow?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:27"/>
               <l>Yet, be couragious, yeeld not vnto Euill:</l>
               <l>Reſiſt beginnings, and deſie the Deuill.</l>
               <l>And for defence amid theſe fierce Alarmes,</l>
               <l>Quicke buckle-on theſe aye-victorious Armes.</l>
               <l>Firſt, <hi>gird</hi> thy loines with <hi>Truth:</hi> thy boſom dreſſe</l>
               <l>With the ſure <hi>Breſt-plate</hi> of pure <hi>Righteouſneſſe:</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:27"/>
               <l>Put on thy head the <hi>Helmet</hi> of <hi>Saluation:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vpon thy feet <hi>Shooes</hi> of the <hi>Preparation</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of the <hi>Glad-Newes</hi> of <hi>Peace:</hi> vpon thine arme</l>
               <l>The <hi>Shield</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> (ſhot-free from euery harme)</l>
               <l>Hel's fiery darts repel thou with the ſame,</l>
               <l>And through it's ſplendor quench their flame with flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:28"/>
               <l>Take in thy hand the bright two-edged <hi>Sword</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of God's ſoule-parting, marrow-piercing <hi>Word.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus compleat-arm'd from God's own <hi>Arcenall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And neuer ceaſing on his Name to call,</l>
               <l>Thou queſtionleſſe ſhalt quickly ouercome</l>
               <l>The World, the Fleſh, Sin, Death, &amp; Hell, in ſum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:13146:28"/>
               <l>And ſo (through CHRIST thy Captain &amp; thy King)</l>
               <l>Of Sin, thy Selfe, and Sathan triumphing,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt (in fine) the happy crowne obtaine,</l>
               <l>And in th'eternall promis'd Kingdome raigne.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:29"/>
            <p>LONDON,
<hi>Printed by</hi> MELCH. BRADWOOD <hi>for</hi>
EDWARD BLOVNT.
1607.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13146:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
